Go. Today's דף *daf* is קנ"ג *kuf nun gimmel*. We start with
some אגדתא *aggadata* that will wrap up the whole interesting disquisition about
old age and death. Fascinating little discussion the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had
related to the issue about dealing with somebody who is dying in
general and on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, and then we'll start the new
פרק perek *perek*. So we ended with the top line of קנ"ג
*kuf nun gimmel* עמוד א' *amud aleph*. Or that's, excuse me, we
begin with the top line of קנ"ג *kuf nun gimmel* עמוד א'
*amud aleph*. אמר amar, רב Rav, יהודה Yehuda בריה דרב שמואל בר
שילת משמיה דרב *Amar Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilas mishmei
d'Rav*, so says רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל *Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav
Shmuel* bar שילת *Shilas* in the name of רב *Rav*. מהספדו של
אדם ניכר אם בן עולם הבא ben olam haba. הוא אם לאו
lav *Me'hespeddo shel adam nikkar im ben olam haba hu im lav*.
So we went from discussing, right, about the whole issue about when
the soul fully departs and when does it remain hovering over and
whether actually the bodies even decompose of righteous people. So we dealt
with old age, we dealt with death, now we're dealing with the
funeral. And it says, from the eulogy of a person, you can
tell if he is a... if he deserves, you know, if he
merits the world to come or not. So which is pretty funny
because, you know, some people exaggerate a good deal in eulogies. People
always exaggerate. Yeah, exactly, but tell if it's exaggerated or how much,
you know. So what? So you subtract the exaggeration, you still have
a good idea of who the person was. There's a lovely רמב"ן
*Ramban* that I love that says, it's forbidden to lie in eulogies
or exaggerate in eulogies more than is the norm.
So anyway, you know, it's like when you write a letter of
recommendation, everybody expects you to sort of like inflate it a certain
amount, so if you're too honest about it, then it's not fair
either. Anyway. All right, so anyway, so you can tell if a
person is deserving of the world to come. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says is that really true? איני *Ini*? Is that really true?
והא אמר ליה Amar lei, רב לרב שמואל בר שילת *V'ha amar
lei Rav l'Rav Shmuel bar Shilas*, רב *Rav* said to רב שמואל
בר שילת *Rav Shmuel bar Shilas*, אחים בהספדא דהתם קאימנא *achim be'hespeda
d'hasam kamina*. I want you to warm the people up, like get
them, you know, heated up, get them emotional
in the eulogy where I am standing, where I am standing means
my eulogy. So when you eulogize me in my funeral, I want
you to do it in a way that gets people very emotional.
So why did he have to say that? If, you know, if
a person is a righteous and merits the world to come, then
you shouldn't need extra effort, it should just be natural when you
talk about the person it should lead to the appropriate type of
emotional response. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא lo קשיא *lo
kashya*, it's not difficult. הא דמחממו ליה ואחים והא דמחממו ליה ולא
אחים *Ha d'mchammu lei v'achim, v'ha d'mchammu lei v'lo achim*. Sometimes, you
know, in one time there could be a scenario where you try
to get people דחם *d'cham* like heated up, you try to get
them emotional and they actually respond and they do get emotional, and
in the other case you could try and not succeed. So what
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* actually says here, when it says מהספדו של אדם
*me'hespeddo shel adam*, it doesn't mean just or even the words that
are being said that how much a person is praised in the
eulogy, but it really means how the person is, how the ציבור
tzibur *tzibur* is responding to the eulogy, how much are they, you
know, sort of crying and mourning and wailing. By the way, you
know, nowadays obviously we make eulogies more of like a celebration of
life, but in the past, you know, it seemed very clear from
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that the goal of the eulogy and they
had מקוננות *mekoninot* was really to get everybody crying and wailing and
to get, you know, get this very public emotional response. So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says that's really what it means, based on the type
of the way the people are responding and how torn up they
are over this person shows whether this person, you know, was is
deserving of the world to come. So it says, ah, but what
do you mean, it required effort to get them emotional? Fine, it
requires effort, but nevertheless sometimes the effort is successful and that's really
somebody, sometimes it's not successful. Now, why did it require effort if
the person if it was such a terrible loss? So there's a
very interesting רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says like this, four
lines down in the narrow lines, הא דמחממו ליה *ha d'mchammu lei*,
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says להספדא ואחים לעולם חימומא בעי *l'hespeda v'achim l'olam
chimmuma ba'ei*, it really does require getting people worked up. Why? Why
isn't that just the natural response? שאין בני אדם נכמרים כל כך
על זקן *she'ein bnei adam nichmarim kol kach al zaken*, because people
normally don't get so torn up when a person dies after old
age. Like if a person קיין עין הרע *kein ayin hara* dies
at the age of 100, you know, we just had somebody sitting
שבעה *shiva* in this community, his mother passed away קיין עין הרע
*kein ayin hara*, she had just passed her 100th birthday, so, you
know, it's so it's like, you know, people are somewhat expecting it
and the person lived a full life. So those so sometimes people
don't always respond,
even if it was a terrible loss. But so therefore sometimes it
really requires getting people emotional, working them up, but nevertheless you can
see how righteous a person was based on how the people are
responding to those efforts. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
אמר ליה amar lei, אביי לרבה *Amar lei Abaye l'Rabba*, so אביי
*Abaye* said to רבה *Rabba*, כגון מר *kegon mar* like the master,
meaning like you רבה *Rabba*, דסני ליה כולי פומבדיתא Pumbedisa, *d'sane lei
kulei Pumbedisa*, all the people of פומבדיתא Pumbedisa *Pumbedisa* hate you because
you are, you know, you really try to give a מוסר *mussar*
and what was what's the line of רבי Rebbe ישראל סלנטר *Rabbi
Yisrael Salanter*? Somebody who, what is
it, who's if the people don't... ach, I can't remember, it's a
really good line about And you meant... do you know what I'm
talking about? Anyway. Okay, the point is that if you're not getting
some people angry at you, you're not doing something right because you
know obviously you're not giving them the מוסר that they need and
you're not standing up to them when they need to be stood
up to. So רבא, Rabba, the people of פומבדיתא, רש"י Rashi says,
you know, were very deceitful and had there were like real problems.
פומבדיתא was a very cosmopolitan town and רבא Rabba would stand up
to them and he would get and everybody would hate him. So
he says, but you, for example, you, that you got the whole
city hating you, so מאן אחים הספדייהו, man achim hespedeyhu, who's going
to get people, you know, who's going to get heated up during
the הספד? hesped? Who's going to cry over your loss? Very lovely
conversation to be having. But he said, but the basic point being
is, you can't always judge a person's righteousness based on the response
of the people. Sometimes a person could be very right, you know,
sometimes people person could be not righteous at all but for some
reason, you know, people are very distraught over his loss and sometimes
it could be the reverse. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, מסתייא את ורבא בר רב חנן. mistaya at veRabba bar Rav
Chanan. It would be enough just you and רבא בר רב חנן.
Rabba bar Rav Chanan. If you get torn up over my death
and at the הספד, hesped, then that is all that matters because
you know, because then that's the ציבור that's significant for me, you
know, in terms of that. The others, there's reasons why they're not
and that doesn't somehow detract from my honor or a signal about
who I was, who, you know, my greatness. So אמר amar ליה,
so okay, so that... so בעי מיניה רבי אליעזר מרב. baei minei
Rabbi Eliezer meiRav. So anyway, that was obviously a significant step back
from what the גמרא Gemara had said before, from going to the
pack about like how just do the people, you know, in general
respond? The גמרא Gemara, acknowledges that sometimes that is actually not a
good gauge and here, you know, we're going to sort of shift
the focus to the people who matter, as it were, the people
who are the good gauge when they get warmed up, when they
get, when they, you know, emotional and respond. Okay, so בעי מיניה
רבי אליעזר מרב. baei minei Rabbi Eliezer meiRav. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer asked from רב, איזהו בן עולם הבא? eizehu ben olam haba?
Who is a person that merits the world to come? אמר ליה,
he said to him, ואזניך תשמענה דבר מאחריך לאמר זה הדרך לכו
בו, ve'oznecha tishmanah davar mei'acharecha leimor zeh haderech lechu vo, your ears
will hear something behind you saying,
this is the path you should go by on it, כי תאמינו
וכי תשמאילו, ki sa'aminu vechi sasmilu, go whether to the right or
to the left. So what does that mean? רש"י Rashi says it
means when you die you'll hear like I don't know a heavenly
voice or an angel saying go on this path or this is
the path that others have gone on and then you'll know you
merit the world to come. Okay, well that's not too helpful. How
do you know who's who merits the world to come? Well when
you hear when you die if you're going to get the world
to come then you'll know, so what good does that do? So
the מהרש"א Maharsha says it actually is alluding to a famous מדרש
Midrash that חז"ל Chazal have on the פסוק pasuk by יתרו, Yisro,
where יתרו Yisro says to משה, Moshe, he says, והודעת להם את
הדרך אשר ילכו בה ואת המעשה אשר יעשון, vehodata lahem es haderech
asher yelchu vah ve'es hama'aseh asher ya'asun, which חז"ל Chazal understand that
הדרך אשר ילכו בה haderech asher yelchu vah means to act in
like ethical ways in terms of, you know, burying the dead and
taking care of the poor and גמילות חסדים gemilus chasadim and לפנים
משורת הדין, lifnim mishuras hadin, so that that's what... so that is
sort of seen as a very similar פסוק pasuk here about הדרך
אשר ילכו בה haderech yelchu vah looking in general at a person's
sort of, you know, ethical and interpersonal behavior and that's the way
you know if he deserves the world to come. Why this specific
פסוק pasuk from יתרו? Yisro? Yeah that's a good question. I don't
know. Because maybe this one also alludes to the idea of death,
אחריך, acharecha, means like after you die. So I'll just read you
briefly the line from the מהרש"א. Maharsha. He says, הדרך זו גמילות
חסדים, haderech zu gemilus chasadim,
ילכו זו ביקור חולים, yelchu zu bikur cholim, בה זו קבורה bah
zu kvurah burying other people, כי תאמינו זה הדין וכי תשמאילו לפנים
משורת הדין. ki sa'aminu zeh hadin vechi sasmilu lifnim mishuras hadin. Okay,
so that's the way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it.
Okay. רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina אמר, כל שדעת רבותינו kol sheda'as rabosinu
or רבותיו rabosav נוחין הימנו. nochin heimenu. Anybody whose רביס Rebbes get
נחת nachas from him, you know, so that's somebody who deserves the
world to come. It's his רביס, Rebbes, not his parents, okay. Parents,
you know, okay, whatever, it's the joke about, you know, about the
doctor, I don't know whatever, there's enough parent jokes, doctor jokes. Okay,
anyway, something anyway. Alright, so yeah the one I'm thinking about is
you know so much נחת nachas from one, you know, that joke?
Anyway. Anyway, it's like what's with your daughter? What was that nice
guy she's married to? You know the doctor? Says, Oh they got
divorced. Says אוי, oy, what happened? Well then she married a lawyer.
A lawyer? Very nice. Yeah but then they got divorced. Says what
happened? Well you know then they made she married this I don't
know whatever this you know something else businessman. Oh what happened there?
They got divorced. Says a lawyer, a doctor, a businessman, so much
נחת nachas from one daughter. Anyway
so... anyway, alright, so okay, so anyway, so it's not the parents
who get נחת nachas for this, it's when when your teachers get
נחת nachas from you then you know you're a בן עולם הבא.
Olam Ha-Ba, Okay.
וסבבו בשוק הסופדים, vesovevu bashuk hasofdim, the eulogizers will... back to what?
Back to קהלת, Kohelet, right, will spread out throughout the marketplace. בני
גלילא אמרי: bnei Galila amri: עשה דברים לפני מטתך. asei devarim lifnei
misascha.
Do things that...
in front of your bed, meaning so that when the eulogizers when
they take out your coffin... the eulogizers would go in front of
the bed and they would, you know, wail and oh my and
they'd call out, what a loss, and so on. So do things
so that they will speak about it in front of your bed.
Act in a way in your life that, you know, that that's
what they'll talk about when you die about how... about that to
get people obviously emotional and worked up.
And before you're on your deathbed? What? Before you're on your deathbed,
right?
Before your, or at least... no, no, no. You'll see the next
line. בני יהודה אמרי עשה דברים לאחר מטתך. Bnei Yehuda amri asei
devarim le'achar mitascha. Do things behind your bed. ולא פליגי, Velo pligi,
it's not difficult. מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה, Mar ki'asrei umar
ki'asrei, I'll tell you. מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה. Mar ki'asrei
umar ki'asrei. Each one going according to his place, because would the
eulogizers when they were carrying out the coffin go in front of
the coffin or behind the coffin? Was a different practice in יהודה
and גליל. Galil. But it means act in a way so that's
what they'll speak about when you die. You know, it's like, what
are they going to write on your tombstone? So that's what you
should... I have to tell you by the way, this is actually...
I learned this, I was told this once in a retreat about
that, you know, do you know how the Nobel Prize got... why
Alfred Nobel decided to endow the Nobel Prize? Alfred Nobel, you know
how he made his money, right? Dynamite. So... so he actually... sort
of like the old,
what's-his-name... not...
who wrote Tom Sawyer? Mark Twain. Mark Twain, the old story with
Mark Twain, you know, which is like, you know, the rumors of
my demise have been greatly exaggerated. So apparently there was a, you
know, they thought... there was a report out that he had died
in a newspaper, Alfred Nobel. And the newspaper printed his eulogy... and
he was alive. Talk about hearing your eulogy. And basically all it
spoke about, you know, his not eulogy, his obit. And all it
spoke about was that he had invented dynamite and how many, you
know, hundreds of thousands of deaths had been resulted from this invention.
And he read this and he said, oh my God, he said,
this is the legacy that I'm leaving behind. And that inspired him
to take his money and to endow the Nobel Prize. So somebody
says that like, you know, this apparently is an exercise that they
do for, you know, executives or whatever, is that they have people
write their, you know, write their eulogy. So, right, or write their
obit. You know, what do you want them to say about you
when you die? You know, and really sort of like makes you
think about how are you directing your life and what are the
goals and what are you trying to achieve. So, you know, this
is sort of what it's saying. You know, do things so that
that'll be the things you want them to say about you when
you die. That should what it... should be what appears in your
obituary. Okay, so now the Gemara continues. But actually it's a really...
it's a real... it's pretty powerful to think about that. Like if
they were to write your obituary about you now, what would they
write? And what do you want them to be writing about you?
You know, and how do you get from here to there? Okay.
תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over there. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi
Eliezer omer: שוב יום אחד לפני מיתתך. Shuv yom echad lifnei mitascha.
So do תשובה teshuvah one day before you die. Alright, so now
we're talking about death. So one is about, you know, how you
know you got עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba what you should do to
plan for it, and now it's about making sure that you, you
know, that you have done תשובה. teshuvah. שאלו תלמידיו את רבי אליעזר.
Sha'alu talmidav es Rabbi Eliezer. So the students asked Rabbi Eliezer: וכי
אדם יודע איזהו יום ימות? Vechi adam yodea eizehu yom yamut? What
do you mean the day before you die? Do you know the
day you'll die? אמר להן: Amar lahen: וכל שכן! Vechol sheken! Great!
ישוב היום, Yashuv hayom, so you should do תשובה teshuvah today. שמא
ימות למחר Shema yamut lemachar because maybe you'll die tomorrow. So every
day you should be doing תשובה teshuvah because you have to make
sure that you die in a state of תשובה. teshuvah.
ונמצא כל ימיו בתשובה Venimtsa kol yamav bitshuva and then every... your
entire life will be one in תשובה. teshuvah. So it's not just
preparing for your death, it's sort of using the, the, you know,
the, the concern of the day of death as a way of
living a more righteous life right now, right? So it's a very...
like it's almost like a strategy. It's not just what you do
so that you'll get עולם הבא Olam HaBa, when you die. It's
by thinking about to ensure that, it'll lead to a much more
righteous life in this world that you'll always be
עומד בתשובה. omed bitshuva. ואף שלמה אמר בחכמתו, Ve'af Shlomo amar bechochmato,
and even Shlomo said in his wisdom: בכל עת יהיו בגדיך לבנים
ושמן על ראשך אל יחסר. Bechol eis yihyu vegadecha levanim veshemen al
roshcha al yechsar. All times your clothes should be white and the
oil on your head should not be lacking, which means you should
ensure your clothes are white, which means רש"י Rashi says your soul
is white, your soul is clean, you've done תשובה. teshuvah. מהרש"א Maharsha
says here clothes means actually different than before, where we were speaking
about your, you know, the soul that I gave you, here it's
talking about the things that like dress the soul, the clothes, which
means your actions. Your actions should always be at all times pure
and if you've done a wrong action you should do תשובה teshuvah
on it. And the "shemen al roshcha"... we'll get to it. Okay,
but anyway more of a focus again though on for the מהרש"א
Maharsha on actions than on the soul. אמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי:
Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakai: משל למלך, Mashal lemelech, now the comparison
to the king is very similar to what we said yesterday. משל
למלך שזימן את עבדיו לסעודה, Mashal lemelech sheziman es avadav lise'uda, a
king invited his his servants to a meal, a feast. ולא קבע
להם זמן, Velo kava lahem zman, he didn't say when it was
going to be. He says, we're going to be having the meal,
you know, you know, sometime in the next year. פקחין שבהן: Pikchin
shebahen: קישטו את עצמן וישבו על פתח בית המלך. Kishu es atzman
veyashvu al pesach beis hamelech. The wise ones, they, you know, got
themselves looking up very fancy, very nice, and they stood by the
king's door. אמרו: Amru: כלום חסר לבית המלך? Klum chaser leveise hamelech?
You know, is anything lacking for the king's house? Meaning he could
make the... he could make his feast instantaneously, you know, without any
warning. So he doesn't require... it takes two seconds to get a
feast going in the king's house. So we'll always be ready. טפשים
שבהם, tipshim shebahem, the foolish ones, הלכו למלאכתן, halchu l'mlachtan, they went
off there to their work. אמרו, amru, כלום יש סעודה ולא טורח?
klum yesh seuda v'lo torach?
Is there ever going to be, you know, there won't be a
meal without any effort? We'll have enough forewarning before you know before
the meal that we'll be able to go home and shower and
get dressed. ופתאום, upitom, suddenly, ביקש המלך את עבדיו, bikesh hamelech et
avadav, the king requested his servants. פיקחים שבהם נכנסו לפניו כשהן מקושטים,
pikchim shebahem nichnasu l'fanev k'shehen mekushatin, the wise people, the smart ones
came in when they were nicely dressed. והטיפשים נכנסו לפניו כשהן מלוכלכים,
v'atipshim nichnasu l'fanev k'shehen meluchlachin, and the foolish ones came in when
they were dirty, you know. And of course this is obviously I
mean the metaphor or the you know in is very powerful because
you know right because people assume like you know people assume you
know you're not going to live a long life, I have plenty
of time to you know to start living a better life, to
do תשובה teshuvah and you know whatever. We people aren't aware you
know. I mean my god there was just a terrible story what
was it about that couple whatever. I mean but you know but
it yeah you know sometimes חס ושלום chas v'shalom tragedy hits suddenly
without any warning so you can't wait around thinking oh I'll have
time. What's that? דלכשתפנה אשנה שמא לא תפנה. da-liksh'tifne efne shema lo
tipne.
Exactly. So אמר הללו, halalu, okay so he got he was happy
for those. וכעס לקראת טיפשים v'kaas likrat tipshim and he was angry
when he greeted the foolish people. אמר הללו שקישרו עצמן לסעודה, amar
halalu shekishru atzman l'seuda, these that dressed themselves up for the meal,
ישבו ויאכלו, yeshvu v'yochlu, they can come in and eat וישתו v'yishtu
and drink. הללו שלא קישרו עצמן לסעודה, halalu shelo kishru atzman l'seuda,
those that did not prepare themselves for the meal, יעמדו ויראו, yaamdu
v'yiru, should stand and watch and therefore you know it'll be terrible
they're watching everybody else enjoying themselves and they're not they're not getting
anything. By the way it's less bad it seems than the גמרא
Gemara before which they were sort of you know sent גיהנום Gehennom
and so on. Alright anyway but this might be this
might be a form of גיהנום. Gehennom. But it might be allegorical.
Well it's all right I mean it was presumably somewhat allegorical before
as well. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara. says חתנו של רבי מאיר
משום רבי מאיר אומר, chosno shel Rabbi Meir mishum Rabbi Meir omer,
the son-in-law of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says in the name of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Who it's surprising they don't say who it was.
I know maybe it was somebody that never said anything else except
this one teaching he had in his life.
Does he mean his father-in-law? No. His daughter's husband? Yeah. Doesn't mean
he's...
alright I don't know. So אמר אף הן נראין
כמשמשין...
amar af hein
nirin
k'mashmashin...
yeah
חתן chatan can sometimes be father-in-law and sometimes be son-in-law. חנניה
בן...
Chananiah ben...
I think it more usually is true in the תורה Torah אני
חותנך יתרו בא אליך, ani chotench Yitro ba eilecha, but you know
but it's also חתניו ולוקחי בנותיו, chatanav v'lokchei b'notav, more commonly it
means son-in-law than father-in-law. חמיו chamiv is father-in-law. So anyway okay אמר
אף הן נראין
כמשמשין, amar af hein nirin k'mashmashin, even they seem as they are
you know as though they are attending to those at the meal
if they're standing around them, you know that's what the butlers do
or you know that's what you know they stand in the back
and they ask people and so they look like they're participating so
that's more than they deserve. אלא, ella, so here's what happened. אלו
ואלו יושבין, elu v'elu yoshvin, they are all sitting. הללו אוכלין, halalu
ochlin, these those eat, והללו רעבין v'halalu re'evin and the others are
not allowed to eat. They have to sit at the table and
not eat, so somehow that's more of a sense of exclusion than
actually standing you know standing around the
table. Standing up behind those that are eating seems like you're somehow
participating. This makes it clear that you're being excluded. You're sitting at
the table and you're not allowed to
eat. הללו שותין, halalu shotin, these are
drinking, והללו צמאים v'halalu tzemayim and the others are thirsty, שנאמר, shene'emar,
כה אמר השם הנה עבדי יאכלו ואתם תרעבו, koh amar Hashem hinei
avadai yocheilu v'atem tir'avu, so says God behold my servants will eat
and you will go hungry. הנה עבדי ישתו ואתם תצמאו, hinei avadai
yishtu v'atem titzma'u, my servants will drink and you will go thirsty.
הנה עבדי ירנו מטוב לב, hinei avadai yaronu mi'tuv lev, they will
rejoice from goodness of heart, ואתם תצעקו מכאב לב v'atem titzaku mikh'eiv
lev and you will cry out from the hurt of heart. So
that's what if you do not do תשובה teshuvah thinking that you
have time this is what will be
your result. דבר אחר בכל עת יהיו בגדיך לבנים, davar acher b'chol
eit yihyu v'gadecha l'vanim, at all times your clothes should be white.
אלו ציצית, elu tzitzit, ציצית tzitzit because of the white strings of
the ציצית. tzitzit. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says what does בכל עת
b'chol eit here mean at all times? It means even if you
don't have the תכלת techelet so they're only white and they're not
the white with the blue you should still have to wear them.
ושמן על ראשך אל יחסר v'shemen al roshcha al yechsar and do
not be lacking the oil on your head. אלו תפילין, elu tfillin,
the תפילין tfillin of the head. So again the מהרש"א Maharsha said
even if you don't have the תפילין tfillin of the יד yad
make sure you know you should at least have the תפילין tfillin
of the head that these things exist you know even with even
in their incomplete form that's how he reads like at all times.
It could just also be saying the classic idea that the גמרא
Gemara says in ברכות Berakhot in other places that if a person
meaning a man is wearing ציצית tzitzit and תפילין tfillin and surrounded
by מצוות mitzvot it ensures more that they will be leading a
virtuous life. So before this ends I'll just say you know this
thing about the sitting at the meal and eating I very much
like this one משל, mashal, it reminds first of all the גמרא
Gemara in a number of places says you know. אין, ein, you
know it says something like what is it? Like, אין גיהנום לצדיקים?
ein Gehenom l'tzaddikim? Is it אין גיהנום? ein Gehenom? Not לצדיקים, l'tzaddikim,
לרשעים. l'reshaim. אלא, Ela, I think it's אין גיהנום אלא ein Gehenom
ela who says what happens is that the sun comes out, הקדוש
ברוך הוא מוציא חמה מנרתיקה, Hakadosh Baruch Hu motzi chamma m'nartika, God
takes the sun out of its like, out of its you know,
out of its
protective bag, and it says, you know, the the צדיקים, tzaddikim, you
know,
prosper in it, you know, from the sunlight and the warmth and
the heat, and the רשעים reshaim are destroyed by it, which some,
you know, which means that it's like the same experience but somehow
for the צדיקים tzaddikim it's a reward and for the רשעים reshaim
it's a, you know, it's an עונש. onesh. So it's, so in
a similar, in a in a similar way, you know, you could
say if everybody has to be living a virtuous life and it's
some type of a virtuous existence then that could be a real,
you know, a real גיהנום Gehenom for the רשעים. reshaim. So I
heard a beautiful like משל mashal which is very much based on
similar to this גמרא, Gemara which is it says like, you know,
it says עולם הבא, he says, you know, somebody goes and he
sees and he sees גיהנום. Gehenom. And he sees that they're all
sitting in front of a feast with the most amazing delicious food.
He says the only problem is is that they they can't bend
their elbows. Their arms are like this, so they can't they can't
eat, so they're starving. Then he goes up to גן עדן Gan
Eden and he sees the exact same thing, and their arms are
also stiff. He says but everybody is taking the food and feeding
the person next to them. Beautiful, isn't
it? So alright and with that thought הדרן עלך שואל. Hadran Alach
Sho'el. So that was a very interesting end of that פרק perek.
of a discussion about death and dying and הספד hesped and so
on. We now enter, we welcome our new a new guest to
our group. Welcome. So we now continue to the next, the what?
Perfect timing. The new פרק. perek, Okay, yes.
He said the the why?
Next and last.
Yeah, the הספדים hespedim changed and now that you know we've celebrate
life as opposed to bewail its loss. Yeah, so is there any
like הלכות halachot about that? Like you know like that you're not
supposed to do one or do the other or it just kind
of just changes with the times?
No, it's similar to the questions you're always asking about how do
these things evolve. Yeah, I mean there's you know there's what to
be said about that. I mean look, some of the whole idea
that you don't give a הספד hesped on you know on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed and other types of days was because a הספד
hesped almost always entailed like crying and wailing. Now sometimes it does.
Sometimes just speaking about a person's life, you know you know even
without the purpose of trying to get people to cry leads to
that, right? So but yeah what are, you know but I think
those things are less are more cultural. Like it never's like in
you know ensconced in הלכה halacha that you have to try to
get everybody worked up. I mean obviously the גמרא Gemara here assumes
that that's what you're trying to do but you know but that
doesn't become הלכה. halacha. All right, so now let's now we begin
the next and last
פרק, מי שהחשיך בדרך. Mi Shehecheshich Bederech. So you know the last
few פרקים prakim were very practical issues around the house mostly in
the kitchen. Now we're dealing with a scenario about somebody caught outside
of the house as שבת Shabbat begins. So it got late and
you're on the way and you have you know you have your
wallet with you, you have your donkey and all of your bags
with you. It's like you know you're stuck in your car and
it's it's about to be שקיעה. shkiya. Okay so what do you
do? נותן כיסו לנכרי, noten kiso l'nochri, you give your wallet to
the non-Jew. ואם אין עמו נכרי, v'im ein imo nochri, if there's
no non-Jew with you, or maybe you don't trust him, ומניחו על
החמור, u'manicho al hachamor, you put it on the donkey. Now assuming
you've got a donkey. Okay so
הגיע לחצר החיצונה, higi'a l'chatzer hachitzona, you come to the outer courtyard
in the you know within the city you finally got out from
traveling between cities and the courtyards would be רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid,
they'd be surrounded with walls made out of the houses. So you're
now in a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. נוטל את הכלים הניטלים בשבת,
notel et hakelim hanitalim b'Shabbat, you now can take off of the
donkey the non-מוקצה muktze כלים. kelim. ושאינם ניטלים בשבת, v'she'einam nitalim b'Shabbat,
and the ones that are מוקצה, muktze, what do you do? מתיר
החבלים והשקים נופלים מאליהם, matir hachavalim v'hasakim noflim me'aleihem, you just undo
the ropes and it assumes that the ropes are קשר שאינו של
קיימא kesher she'eino shel kayama and you're allowed to undo it on
שבת Shabbat and the you know and the stuff just falls down
so you get it off the donkey but you don't actually move
it because it's מוקצה. muktze. You know you have scenarios somebody comes
in again it's already שבת Shabbos, and they're carrying you know their
luggage and they have their wallet in their luggage and similar questions.
How do you deal with the מוקצה? muktze? How do you deal
with you know to get the non-מוקצה muktze out and so on?
What you could ask the נכרי nochri who might have been with
you to take it inside?
Well right, maybe it's going in the case where there isn't a
נכרי, nochri, where there's just a חמור. chamor. Okay but they're now
going to be interesting questions because a couple questions. First of all
you know well let's just start with if you're asking the non-Jew
that should be at least a rabbinic problem of אמירה לעכו"ם amira
l'akum having a non-Jew do מלאכה melacha for you. And if you're
putting it on a donkey that should maybe even be a biblical
problem of using working your animals. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara will get to both of those
but it's and it starts with the first one. מאי טעמא שרו
ליה רבנן למיתב כיסיה לנכרי? Mai ta'ama sharu lei rabanan l'meitav kiseih
l'nochri? Why did the rabbis allow you to give your wallet to
the non-Jew? Because I mean that's at least a rabbinic problem. So
the גמרא Gemara says קים להו לרבנן Kim lehu l'rabanan because the
rabbis have determined דאין אדם מעמיד עצמו על ממונו. de'ein adam ma'amid
atzmo al mamono. דאין אדם מעמיד עצמו על ממונו. dein adam maamid
atzmo al mamono. A person is not going to stand idly by
regarding his money. You could be the frum guy, but my God,
you want me to throw out my
wallet? Somehow you rationalize it and you keep your wallet on your
person. So אי לא שרית ליה ei lo sharis lei and therefore
if you do not find a way to permit him with a
lesser problem with a lesser prohibition, אתי לאתויי ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים.
asai l'asuyei arba amos b'reshus harabim.
He's just going to wind up carrying it anyway. So it's quite
interesting where the גמרא Gemara sometimes realizes that you're so anxious and
perturbed
that we have to find a way to make it מותר muttar
or else you're just going to do it regardless even באיסור. be'issur.
We had a whole discussion about when a fire breaks out and
so on. So here, you have a very similar issue about having
to leave your money and leave your property behind. Yes.
So this reason is to prevent דאורייתא d'Oraisa איסור issur of carrying
in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. What if you're in a
כרמלית?
carmelis? Will they allow that? So we'll take a look. We'll keep
on seeing. I mean there are other types of things that they
could have allowed and we'll see that they did allow. So let's
keep on going.
Because the גמרא Gemara we say tell a נכרי nochri
to put it out, didn't we? Right, there we did say that
אין אומרים לו כבה ואל תכבה. ein omrim lo kavei v'al tichbei.
That is true.
So why don't we do that? I mean we're already ממון, mamon,
he's going to lose it, so...
It's
a good question, how they assess those scenarios differently. Either about how
anxious you'll be and how you'll act or what would be the
consequences that's maybe more of a public event this is a more
private one maybe we can give you a little bit more latitude
here because it's private. It's not exactly clear, that's where a very
often recurring phrase you hear is like אין דומה גזירות חז"ל זו
לזו. ein domeh gezeiros Chazal zu l'zu.
You can't compare because every one seems to be
there doesn't seem to be good rules about how to abstract and
apply from one case to the other. Okay, so אמר רבה, amar
Rabbah, so says Rabbah, דוקא כיסו. davka kiso. This is only now
we're going to try to put some limits on it. This is
only your wallet. אבל מציאה לא. aval metzia lo. If you found
something in the middle of the street on שבת, Shabbos we're not
going to let you have a non-Jew carry it for you. Because
then we're not afraid that you'll break שבת Shabbos. for that. It's
not your own money and therefore we're not afraid you'll be so
anxious that you'll break שבת. Shabbos So גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא כיסו
תניא. pishita kiso tanya. Of course, it says your wallet. No, מהו
דתימא ma d'teima I might have thought הוא הדין אפילו מציאה. hu
hadin afilu metzia. It would be the same it would apply even
if you found an object. והא דתני כיסו v'ha d'tani kiso why
did it say wallet? אורחא דמילתא קתני. orcha d'milsa kasani. It's just
the natural the standard case is you've got your wallet on you.
But really it would apply to anything. קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that that's not true. That when it's talking about a found
object that we are not concerned that you will violate Shabbat. Then
he says, however now he goes back in the opposite direction, ולא
אמרן אלא דלא אתי לידיה. v'lo amran ela d'lo asai l'yadei.
That's only if the object is still on the street, you haven't
picked it up. אבל אתי לידיה aval asai l'yadei once you picked
it
up, ככיסיה דמי k'kisei dami then you treat it like your wallet.
Oh my God, we already had the money in hand. Now you're
asking me to leave over money that I just
found, that's my money, I picked it up. So therefore and we're
afraid that you'll break שבת Shabbos, unless we find a permitted way
to allow you to do it. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some say,
בעא רבה baei Rabbah he asked this question. מציאה הבאה לידו מהו.
metzia habaa l'yado mahu.
Let's say it's a lost object that you actually picked up. What
do we say? כיון דאתי לידו ככיסיה דמי. keivan d'asai l'yado k'kisei
dami.
Do we say since it came to your hand it's like your
wallet? או דלמא כיון דלא טרח בה o dilma keivan d'lo tarach
bah since there was no effort, it was like just מן השמים,
min hashamayim, לאו ככיסיה דמי lav k'kisei dami it's not like your
wallet and we're not afraid you'll break שבת, Shabbos. תיקו teiku and
we don't know the answer. You know, so there are stories about
this about someone who found some significant thing in the street and
they basically just stood there the whole שבת. Shabbos. Like let's say
you find a hundred dollar bill you stand on it the whole
שבת. Shabbos You don't move it, it's not מוקצה muktzah so you
just stand on it. There are things that you could do and
I assume you all know the joke right about the חסידים Chasidim
comparing their רבנים? Rabbanim? My Rabbi is so great, one שבת Shabbos
it was raining and he said and he had to get home
and he was going to get soaked. He said וואסער אהין וואסער
אהער vasser ahin vasser aher and the rain split and he walked
down the middle. That was like ha, that's nothing, my Rabbi it
was one שבת Shabbos, he was going and there was a huge
river and there was no way he was going to get across.
So he said וואסער אהין וואסער אהער vasser ahin vasser aher and
he walked through the middle. Other guy said pff, he said my
רבי once was walking home on שבת, Shabbos. and there in the
street, hundred dollars, hundred dollar bill, but what was he going to
do? It was שבת. Shabbos So he said
שבת אהין שבת אהער Shabbos ahin Shabbos aher picked up the hundred
dollars. All right.
So there you go. So even for a מציאה metzia there's a
definite יצר הרע. yetzer hara. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says
certainly if he didn't let pick it up then
then we're not overly concerned that we need to find an allowance
for you. I'll actually get back to that because רמב"ם Rambam says
that even in that case there would be something that would be
permissible to do.
פחות פחות מארבע אמות? pachas pachas me'arba amos?
Yeah, but let's not get there yet. אין עמו נכרי. ein imo
nochri. Now if there's no non-Jew, then you put it on the
donkey. So גמרא Gemara says, טעמא דאין עמו נכרי. ta'ama d'ein imo
nochri. The reason is that there's no non-Jew. הא יש עמו נכרי
נכרי עדיף. ha yesh imo nochri nochri adif.
But if there is a non-Jew, better to give it to the
non-Jew than to put it on the donkey. Why? מאי טעמא mai
ta'ama what's the reason? חמור אתה מצווה על
שביתתו. chamor atah metzuveh al shevisaso. For donkey you're commanded to make
sure that it rests. Your donkey you can't work your
donkey. So לא תעשה כל מלאכה Lo taaseh kol melacha and says
שביתת בהמתו. Shevitat behemto. Therefore you're commanded to let it rest. So
the question's going to be how would it be allowed then anyway?
We'll get to that. But נכרי, nochri, אי אתה מצווה על שביתתו,
ee ata mitzuveh al shevitato, but not by a non-Jew. Okay, so
there's no, he's not under your control, and therefore you don't have
to ensure that he rests. And therefore, it is not a biblical
violation, it's only rabbinic.
Okay, and that's why everyone goes there in this case.
Right. And therefore and here they allowed it. Now the גמרא Gemara's
tries to set up the whole hierarchy. חמור וחרש שוטה וקטן. Chamor
ve-cheresh shoteh ve-katan.
Let's say you have with you a donkey and a
deaf-mute, somebody who is like not of right mind, like somebody
insane, and a קטן, katan, a minor. So who is the better
person to give it to? Anybody in the last three categories is
exempt, is not yet obligated, is not yet an adult. So which
is better? Them or the donkey? חמור מנח ליה, Chamor manach lay,
חרש שוטה וקטן לא יהיב ליה. Cheresh shoteh ve-katan lo yahiv lay.
Better put it on the donkey and not give it to one
of those. Not obvious at all, because the donkey you have a
מצווה mitzvah to ensure that the donkey rests and we're going to
have to talk about in a minute how you avoid violating the
biblical prohibition. Who says he's your son? Okay, these could be unrelated
to you. So therefore it's not at all obvious that you would
put it on the donkey. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? הני אדם הני
לאו אדם. Hani adam hani lav adam.
Because actually there's a quite fascinating גמרא Gemara that rather than giving
more weight to the immediate technical question of which one could lead
to an איסור דאורייתא, issur de-oraita, the donkey is more likely to
lead to an איסור דאורייתא issur de-oraita of having your donkey work
for you, it looks at it more broadly from a
חינוך chinuch perspective. Basically says
the donkey doesn't know what's going on. These are people and you
allow this and maybe they'll, the קטן katan will grow up, maybe
they'll get better, the other two people get better, and if not
anyway, so it'll lead to giving, it'll lead to adults doing the
same type of a thing, so you have to be more concerned
about the implications than about the immediate technical question of whether this
might lead to working your donkey.
Did we already have a case with the kid where he was
like the best instance or something and he had a coin and
then there was a question about hugging?
Yeah, about picking up somebody that had the stone in their hand,
right?
Right, stone in the hand or it was like a kid who
had
a pocket full of change? Right. And he'll drop it and you'll
come to pick it up.
Right. And by that it seemed like it was fine. Or his
kid had a pocket full of change?
Right, well, if your child does, so that's a separate question about
what is the idea that you're commanded regarding the work of your
child and that's primarily when he's doing stuff for you, not for
himself. How is it different for a non-Jew? Because here he would
be doing it for you. Okay, but the point is that that's
only specifically your child. Right, if it's some other minor
then that's not in the biblical category of your child. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that's that hierarchy. חרש ושוטה, cheresh
ve-shoteh, now let's say you have to choose between
a חרש cheresh and a שוטה. shoteh. לשוטה. Le-shoteh. You give it
to a שוטה. shoteh. Why? Because the חרש, cheresh, the deaf-mute, the
גמרא Gemara in other places and we'll see in a minute recognizes
that he has
a certain degree of intelligence, actually there's some opinions that he is
considered a full בר דעת, bar daat, whereas a שוטה shoteh is
considered to be not of right mind at all, at least when
they're in their state
of their mental illness. I should say for all of this that
obviously these are very sensitive issues in terms of it's one thing
to discuss them in the abstract, in the practice about how הלכה
halacha treats people with mental illness, how does הלכה halacha treat people
that are deaf and mute? I actually have to tell you that
for a very long time because a חרש cheresh halachically is only
deaf-mute. If somebody's just deaf, he does not have
halachic disability, physical disability, but not a halachic one. And I always
assumed, oh, so it's not a big deal, I mean how many
deaf people also happen to be mute? But then I realized the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that the way a normal deaf person can
talk, the difficulty he has of enunciating because certainly prior to hearing
aids or whatever because there's none of that audio feedback, so that
that would define him as also as also mute. And therefore a
standard deaf person would actually be in the חרש cheresh category. But
there was an enormous
evolution of הלכה, halacha, certainly since they began schools for the deaf
in the 18th century, and also sign language. And sign language, that's
a question, does that count as
speech? And just sadly not all פוסקים poskim are of that position
that nowadays deaf-mute is not in the category of חרש, cheresh, but
many, many are, that that's no longer an appropriate category
for current people that are deaf-mute. But anyway within the גמרא's Gemara
world where it was giving them that category, it says that a
חרש cheresh שוטה shoteh is at least is even less of a
בר דעת, bar daat, of someone of intellect, and therefore you would
give it to the שוטה. shoteh.
Now,
שוטה וקטן, shoteh ve-katan, between a שוטה shoteh and a minor, לשוטה,
le-shoteh, again you give it to the שוטה shoteh because a minor,
there's a longer-term חינוך chinuch concern about... Because he will become an
adult. איבעיא להו, Iba'ye l'hu, now they raise the
question: חרש וקטן, cheresh ve-kattan, what do you do about a חרש
וקטן? cheresh ve-kattan? On one hand the קטן kattan will become an
adult so now
maybe, maybe he's very young and it's not going to, he doesn't
have דעת daas to be a problem, but he will be an
adult, so it's bad חינוך, chinuch, and the חרש cheresh is an
adult but has some דעת, daas, but doesn't have full דעת. daas.
So מאי, mai, what do you say? אליבא דרבי אליעזר לא תיבעי
לך, Aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer lo tiba'ye lach, according to Rabbi Eliezer I
don't have a question. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa,
רבי יצחק אומר משום רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Yitzchak omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer,
Rabbi Yitzchak says in the name of Rabbi Eliezer,
it's a תוספתא, Tosefta, תרומת חרש לא תצא לחולין מפני שהוא ספק,
Trumas cheresh lo tesei l'chullin mipnei shehu safek, that if a חרש
cheresh takes תרומה, trumah, it doesn't, you cannot assume that it was
ineffective because there's a doubt. A normal חרש cheresh is a doubtful
בר דעת, bar daas, he might be a בר דעת. bar daas.
So הלכה-ly halacha there's a possibility that he has the full status
of an adult. And therefore clearly you would prefer to give it
to a קטן kattan because he might be a full, a full
הלכה-ic halacha adult and obviously he'd be violating שבת Shabbos, if you
were to give it to him. כי תיבעי לך, Ki tiba'ye lach,
what's my question? אליבא דרבנן, Aliba d'Rabbanan, according to the Rabbis that
say it's not effective at all. דתנן, D'nan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, חמישה לא יתרומו ואם תרמו אין תרומתן תרומה, chamishah lo
yitrumu v'im tormu ein trumasam trumah, five can't take תרומה trumah and
if they do it's not effective. אלו הן, Elu hein, and these
are they: חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-kattan, so those three we
just mentioned. והתורם את שאינו שלו, V'hatorem es she'eino shelo, if you
take תרומה trumah on grain that's not yours, only the owner can
take תרומה. trumah. ונכרי שתרם את של ישראל אפילו ברשותו, V'nachri shetaram
es shel Yisrael afilu birshuso, and a non-Jew that takes for the
Jew even if the Jew gives him permission. So that would work
if I did it for you and you gave me permission, but
if a non-Jew is doing it for you, no, because it's a
concept of שליחות, shlichus, agency, which only works if in this case
for another Jew to be my agent for something like תרומה, trumah,
something that requires Jews. Anyway, what's important to us is it says
that if a חרש cheresh takes it, it's not
effective. So in all these cases אין תרומתן תרומה, ein trumasam trumah,
it is not effective. So מאי, mai, so what's the story? A
חרש cheresh does not have, certainly does not have a status of
an adult, it would not be considered
חילול שבת chillul Shabbos like, as an adult. So who do you
give it to, the חרש cheresh or the קטן? kattan? חרש יהיב
ליה, Cheresh yahiv lei, do you give it to the חרש? cheresh?
דקטן אתי לכלל דעת, D'kattan asi l'khlal daas, because the קטן kattan
will in the natural course of things become an adult and be
obligated and therefore it would be really bad חינוך chinuch to give
it to the קטן. kattan. או דילמא, Od deilma, or do you
say, לקטן יהיב ליה, l'kattan yahiv lei, better to give it to
the minor. Why? דחרש אתי לאחלופי בגדול, D'cheresh asi l'achlufei b'gadol, maybe
not again the people in front of you, but maybe the broader
impact of your actions. If you give it to a חרש, cheresh,
people see an adult Jew, you just gave it to him to
be carrying your stuff on שבת, Shabbat, and they'll come to, show
it
too then. Well yes, but then you had a choice of other
better alternatives. Okay, so here's the question: these concerns are there, but
we would like to get the one that is the best of
these choices. So which is the better? איכא דאמרי לקטן יהיב ליה,
Ika d'amri l'kattan yahiv lei, איכא דאמרי לחרש יהיב ליה, ika d'amri
l'cheresh yahiv lei, so there's opinions on both sides. Some say better
give it to the חרש, cheresh, worry about the people immediately in
front of you and the implications. איכא דאמרי לקטן יהיב ליה, Ika
d'amri l'kattan yahiv lei, and some say you give it to the
minor and you have to worry about broader implications. So again, what's
interesting about all of this besides the fascinating hear question of the
hierarchy is the point that there could be a case that right
in the here and now it's more problematic, you're going to give
it to a קטן, kattan, you'll put it on the donkey which
could lead to a violating the obligation to let your animals rest
and so on. But even though it's potentially more problematic right here,
there's also broader implications that might come to play that would change
the priorities. And that's why you certainly put it on your חמור
chamor before you give it to any Jew to carry for you.
Now the גמרא Gemara, goes on, we'll get back again to why
it's not a problem with the חמור, chamor, but now the גמרא
Gemara goes on to speak about down this list of alternatives,
yet another possibility. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אין שם לא נכרי ולא חמור ולא חרש ולא שוטה ולא
קטן. ein sham lo nachri v'lo chamor v'lo cheresh v'lo shoteh v'lo
kattan. You don't have anybody here that you could give it to.
Okay, no animals and no people that are not adult Jews. So
מאי, mai, what do you do? אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
עוד אחרת היתה, od acheres haysa, there was another actual
solution, ולא רצו חכמים לגלותה, v'lo ratzu chachamim l'galosah, but they didn't
want to tell it. They were afraid that if they revealed it,
it would lead to abuse. So of course now the גמרא Gemara
is going to tell us what it is. So it doesn't do
any good if you don't reveal it, and that does lead to
a general concern in הלכה. halacha. Sometimes there are certain approaches which
it's important to know that they're available to you, but on the
other hand if you announce them too publicly
or whatever, it could lead to abuse. So there is a question
about how to manage those types of concerns. So let's see what
the
גמרא Gemara says. Because very often if something
that
for you is a בדיעבד, b'diavad, for somebody else comes to be
a לכתחילה l'chatchilah once these become legitimate options. So anyway, so let's
find out what that was. מאי עוד אחרת היתה? Mai od acheres
haysa? What was this other
thing? מוליכו פחות פחות מארבע אמות. Molicho pachas pachas m'arba amos. You
do tiny little trips, each one less than ארבע אמות. arba amos.
So four, you walk three אמות, amos, let's say about roughly about
five feet, you know, four and a half feet, and then you
stop. Three, three אמות amos and then you stop. So each act
of carrying is defined by picking up, which means starting to move
if it's on your person, and then putting down, which would be
stopping to move if it's on your person. So every single one
is carrying less than the שיעור, shiur, less than four. Actually, it's
not even that. Carrying פחות מארבע אמות pachot me'arba amos without doing
it sequentially could be that that's not even אסור assur at all.
I could just, you know, it's not even defined as carrying. So
I just, you know, to walk two steps is not, but to
do it then sequentially so that they add up to carrying a
long distance is obviously a major concern. And therefore it's easy that
you'll, you'll come to slip up and do a biblical transgression, but
that actually is an option that you could do if you have
no other choice, but they didn't want to tell anybody about it.
So why didn't they use the שיטה? shitta? You know, we had
that before, the שניים שעשו... shnayim she'asu...
okay, that's interesting. That's an interesting question. I don't know. Why didn't
they say that if there was an adult Jew that you could
do it together, you know, type of a שניים שעשו הוא? shnayim
she'asu hu? That's interesting. I don't know.
It's still אסור. assur.
It's still אסור assur also. ארבע פחות מארבע אמות Arba pachot me'arba
amos is אסור. assur.
Not פחות פחות, pachot pachot, sequentially פחות פחות pachot pachot is אסור,
assur, yes.
If they knew there was a solution and they chose not to...
but they are telling. They just told us.
They just told us in the גמרא, Gemara but they may not
have told it as publicly.
So right, you are, it
is a
question.
Right, is the concern...
they want to have control?
No, well, actually we're going to read a line that addresses this
issue about it, but I will tell you, it's not as problematic
when you sort of don't, you know, like if you're teaching I
don't know, a חתן וכלה chatan v'kallah class. הלכה ואין מורין. Halacha
v'ein morin. Right, but you know, but it's true. If you go
ahead and you're teaching a class here all הלכות נידה, hilchos niddah,
do you sort of lay out and בדיעבד bedi'avad if you did
this then you could do this and בדיעבד bedi'avad you could do
this and בדיעבד bedi'avad you could do this, you tell them all
the בדיעבדים, bedi'avads, it's like, you know, doesn't lead to a certain
a strong sense of what what you have to do. You know,
so you could say בדיעבד bedi'avad if you have a problem, you
know, call me and then we'll talk about it, to set up
a certain, I don't think, I know you're going to think it's
about control, but I really do think it's about being concerned for,
because you know, creating, it's like education. You don't tell kids everything
on the first day, you know, there's anyway, there's a question about
setting up some of that. But I don't feel that's as problematic
if you can give me a call and then I can tell
you it's מותר, muttar, right? But here the guy's stuck out outside
of the city. He has nobody to call. So if he doesn't
know, if he doesn't know, there's no way he's going to find
out. So that I think, right... right, so that I think, right.
That I think, so the question is, did it remain that way?
It says לא רצו לגלותו, lo ratzu l'galoto, but maybe in the
end they were going to talk about it. They did. So let's
talk, let's say, but I do think that the idea of not
putting everything on the table לכתחילה lechatchila is not bad if you
signal that if there's a problem then there are solutions and come
talk to me. But in this case, that's not an opportunity because
he's stuck out there in the middle of, you know, outside of
the city. Yes.
Do you think it's also a מוקצה muktzeh problem?
Yeah, but you know, if it's still on your body... well, first
of all, it's a good question. When are you giving it to
the minor or putting it on the donkey? Okay, presumably you're, you
know, maybe there's a question. It might be that you're doing that
ערב erev before it gets dark. Although we'll see in a minute
that you will continue to handle this stuff. So it is true
that implicitly we're sort of waving certain מוקצה muktzeh concerns as well.
Not yet clear about that because you might have done it all
before שבת, Shabbat. but we'll, we'll get back to that.
It also says כלים הניטלין בשבת. keilim hanitallin b'Shabbat.
Right, that's once you get into רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and there's
no longer concern of how you're going to get it to a
protective place, then you have to start once again worrying about, you
know, worrying about מוקצה. muktzeh. But it could be as you're transporting
it, you know, yes.
Plus a תחום techum problem?
תחום Techum could also be an issue, it's true. So, you know,
exactly which types of things would they allow? Those are all good
questions. The גמרא's Gemara not fully spelling that out. And you all,
you know, everything you say is correct. Let's take a look at
where the גמרא Gemara goes with this idea about not, you know,
not telling the whole truth as it were, not giving everything away.
So it says, אמאי לא רצו חכמים לגלותו? amay lo ratzu chachamim
l'galoto? Why did they not want to reveal it? משום mishum because
of the פסוק, pasuk, כבוד אלקים הסתר דבר, kevod Elokim haster davar,
honor to God is hiding of a matter, וכבוד מלכים חקור דבר,
u'kevod melachim chakor davar, honor of kings is investigating a matter. So
רש"י Rashi says sometimes when it's protecting כבוד שמים, kevod shamayim, trying
to prevent people from sinning, sometimes it requires, you know, not, you
know, not spelling everything out. I know this is an idea that
we have a really hard time with, you know, that knowledge, you
know, that there should be some sense of forbidden knowledge. I even
know there's a whole book I have, haven't read it yet, anyway
it's called Forbidden Knowledge, which is why I haven't read it. But
about this idea, you know, that it used to that that that
there's some things that are just dangerous, you know. And what was
that movie with Jack Nicholson? The truth, you can't handle the truth!
Right? So anyway, but the point is is that I think that
that's the same, you know, from a human perspective, וכבוד מלכים חקור
דבר. kevod melachim chakor davar. We should try to find out the
truth, investigate something, you know, to as much as possible, but sometimes
if we're trying to, you
know, encourage, you know... is that the highest value that everybody needs
to know all of the facts. You know, so I do think
that that is a very important question and something you struggle with
as a rabbi that when somebody's asking you something, you don't want
to be patronizing or paternalistic, you want to be straight and give
them all the things and empower them, but to some degree what
they're all also asking you implicitly is give me an answer to
help me keep הלכה. Halacha. Right? They're really, when they say what's
the הלכה Halacha here, to some degree they're not asking just an
abstract philosophical or fact-based question of what the הלכה, Halacha, they're really
saying what, give me an answer that will help me keep the
הלכה. Halacha. So part of that answer
is not spelling out all of the ways in which it might
be permissible because this person might could lead to violation. Maybe that's
really the question they are asking you. So I don't know, it's
something that I struggle with but I do think that it's more
challenging here
because of the issue of what do you call it, because the
guy doesn't have anyone to ask. So what good is it going
to do, there's no way that he can find it out. Yes.
This is the heart of this controversy around Ruth Calderon's wonderful... Yeah,
because that some people hated it because this secular ישיבה, yeshiva, you're
opening up the תורה, Torah, the הלכה. Halacha.
Yeah, but I don't want to bring that in because I understand,
but that's not the same concern here. Here the concern is if
you spell out all of the like leniencies with הלכה, Halacha, it
could lead to violation. So it's a very specific concern to more
observant. Yeah, because you're saying if people know now then they won't
come to carry, they'll find a היתר heter way to do it
rather than an אסור assur way to do it. I understand. I
don't think it's the exact same as the Ruth Calderon debate but
these are similar about how much you make these things all public
knowledge. Right, I understand, I understand. Okay, so let's keep on going.
So מה כבוד אלוהים איכא? Ma kevod Elokim ika?
So what is to how is it protecting the honor of God?
דמטי לאתויי ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים De-mati le-atuyei arba amot bi-reshut ha-rabim
because if you tell this then it could easily lead to
violation. Okay, תניא, Tanya, we turn to a
בריתא: Braisa: רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, בו ביום גדשו סאה,
Bo ba-yom gadshu se'ah, that day
they piled up the סאה se'ah of
grain. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, בו ביום מחקו סאה. Bo
ba-yom machaku se'ah.
I will tell you in a minute. That day they sort of
smoothed out the measure. So the way רש"י Rashi explains what this
means, תוספות Tosafot has a different interpretation, is that what was it,
that רש"י Rashi says that it was perfect what they did. They
made a nice protection for the דאורייתא De-Oraita by giving you all
of, by on the one hand giving you these היתרים, Heterim, and
on the other hand, let me just check רש"י in one
second.
Yeah, so רש"י what just... Oh right, so רש"י says it's exactly
this issue of the פחות פחות מארבע אמות. Pachot pachot mi-arba amot.
Was it a good thing not to tell here, Rivka, not to
tell them to do the פחות פחות מארבע אמות, Pachot pachot mi-arba
amot, to keep it a secret? So the first opinion is yeah,
it was a good thing they like piled up the wheat as
it were, they made another barrier and that's going to help protect
the violation of the דאורייתא. De-Oraita. And the other approach according to
רש"י is no, it's like you pile something on a measure then
you have to smooth it off. You tried to make a bigger
barrier but it's going to lead to it falling down, it's going
to lead to violation, and they should not have hidden this idea
of the ארבע אמות Arba Amot going each sequentially less than ארבע
אמות. Arba Amot. So תניא, Tanya, we turn to a בריתא: Braisa:
משלו של רבי אליעזר למה הדבר דומה? Mashlo shel Rabbi Eliezer le-mah
ha-davar domeh? What's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to be compared to? לקופה
מלאה קישואין ודילועין, Le-kuppah mele'ah kishu'in ve-dilu'in,
like a basket filled with gourds and cucumbers. אדם נותן לתוכה חרדל,
Adam noten le-tochah chardal,
you pour into it mustard, again mustard is mister seeds, right? They
flower into it, והיא מחזקת, Ve-hi machzeket, and it will contain it.
So basically he says that this is a type of a גזירה
Gezeirah that actually can protect people, contain violation. ומשלו של רבי יהושע
למה הדבר דומה? U-mashlo shel Rabbi Yehoshua le-mah ha-davar domeh? What's it
similar to for רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? דומה לעריבה מלאה דבש, Domeh
le-arivah mele'ah devash,
like a kneading trough filled with honey. נותן לתוכה רימונים ואגוזים, Noten
le-tochah rimonim ve-egozim, you try to put things into it, והיא מקיאה,
Ve-hi mekiah, and it spits them out. So you try to fill
it up, you didn't leave any space and it's counter-productive. So he
says, the fact is you try to make something off-limits and in
the end it's like a חומרא Chumra that will lead to a
קולא Kula because it will lead to violation. Okay, but in the
end of the day we actually פוסקים Poskim פחות פחות מארבע אמות
Pachot pachot mi-arba amot and the גמרא Gemara at least revealed it,
so you know that at least is trying to create a balance.
And I should say that רמב"ם, Rambam, fascinating, the רמב"ם Rambam actually
says that in the case going back to the גמרא Gemara about
if you find a מציאה, Metziah, the רמב"ם Rambam says you can't
give it to a נכרי, Nochri, you can't put it on the
donkey, but you know what you can do?
פחות פחות מארבע אמות.
Pachot pachot mi-arba amot. So even though the גמרא Gemara was the
last thing that they allowed. For the רמב"ם Rambam he now the
רמב"ם Rambam was asked about this in a תשובה, teshuvah, says, "What
are you talking about? Like the גמרא Gemara says you can't pick
up the מציאה metziah and whatever," you know. So the רמב"ם Rambam
says, "Yeah, but you know everything else involved other people and was
more public. This פחות פחות מארבע אמות pachot pachot me'arba amot is
more private and therefore actually becomes something that you can even do
for the מציאה." metziah.
Even though the גמרא Gemara didn't say it.
I know, yeah, it's pretty amazing. Okay, the גר"א Gra gives a
גמרא Gemara that could have been the basis for the רמב"ם. Rambam.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר מר, Amar mar, אימא נוכרי eima
nochri now we get to the issue of the donkey. מניחה על
החמור, Menicha al hachamor, you can put it on the donkey. אימא
נוכרי Eima nochri does not a non-Jew put it on the donkey?
ולא מחמר Velo mechamer from the word חמור, chamor, you're leading your
donkey. This word מחמר mechamer leading your donkey becomes the halakhic term
for having your animals do work for you on שבת. Shabbat. So
to participating in your animals doing work for you on שבת. Shabbat
Okay, ורחמנא אמר v'rachamana amar and the תורה Torah says לא תעשה
כל מלאכה lo ta'aseh kol melachah and then it ends with, right,
שורך וחמורך, shorcha vachamorcha, your
ox and your donkey. So even though you're not doing it and
it's not a biblical it's not a violation of שבת Shabbat that
like you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa, it's still transgressing this negative prohibition.
So by the way I should mention that רמב"ם Rambam emphasizes not
that it's a לאו lav, and that you violate the לאו, although
that's what the גמרא Gemara, is saying here, we'll talk about this
more later, but he says it's the עשה aseh of למען ינוח
lema'an yanua'ch שורך וחמורך shorcha vachamorcha so the רמב"ם Rambam says it's
an עשה. aseh. Anyway we'll talk about that more later. Anyway so
how do you get around this violation? דאמר רב אדא בר אבא
De'amar Rav Adda bar Abba מניחה עליה כשהיא מהלכת, menicha aleha k'she'hi
mehalechet,
you wait until the donkey starts walking and then you put it
on. So therefore it will never have done an עקירה. akira. The
donkey will have never because it's defined in the technical terms not
just labor but מלאכה. melachah. So the donkey will never have picked
it up off the ground because it was already walking when you
put it on the donkey. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואי
אפשר דלא קיימא להשתין מים ולהטיל גללים, v'iy efshar d'lo kaima l'hashtin
mayim ul'hateil gelalim, it's going to one time stop to urinate or
to defecate. ואיכא עקירה והנחה V'ika akira v'hanacha then it'll start moving
again so that'll be a and then it'll stop again. So there
will be an עקירה akira and an הנחה. hanacha. So what do
you do? So now here Seth we get to your point about
the about מוקצה. muktzeh. כשהיא מהלכת מניחה עליה, K'she'hi mehalechet menicha aleha,
as it starts walking you put it on it. כשהיא עומדת K'she'hi
omedet when you see it standing now נוטלה הימנה notleh heimena you
remove it from it. So you put it on it as it's
moving, it stops to urinate, you take it off from it, then
you wait until it starts moving again and then you put it
back on. So you're going to have to be very on top
of this donkey as you're getting this back home which is probably
a good thing that it makes you conscious about how where you
know this is you know how we're you know we're
letting you rub up against שבת Shabbat so you have to be
very conscious about being on top of how it's taking place. But
again Seth obviously you'd be moving the מוקצה muktzeh in this case.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi if that's
what you're doing with your donkey חבירו אפילו חבירו, chaveiro afilu chaveiro,
similar to Michael's question except again it's not שנים שעשו shnayim she'asu
but have your friend walk, even not even the adult Jew and
give it to him as he's walking, he continues to walk, he
never did an עקירה. akira.
Or you do it yourself if you know if you're always walking
the whole time.
No, well we'll get to that. So am so אמר רב פפא
amar Rav Papa כל שבגופו חייב חטאת, kol she'begupo chayav chatas, anything
that if you were to do it, you know walk with your
wallet and stop, that you'd be חייב chayav it would be a
biblical transgression of שבת Shabbat בחבירו פטור אבל אסור. b'chaveiro patur aval
assur. By your friend it's forbidden, you're exempt, you know basically you
put it on him as he's walking so there's no עקירה akira
but it's still rabbinically forbidden. כל שבחבירו פטור אבל אסור Kol she'bechaveiro
patur aval assur
anything with your friend is פטור patur but you're exempt from you
know this case of putting it on as he's walking בחמורו מותר
לכתחילה. b'chamoro mutar l'chatchila. It's מותר לכתחילה mutar l'chatchila by your donkey
which sounds even not in the special case of the wallet which
is interesting. It sounds like in general if the if the donkey
is not doing a technical מלאכה melachah because you got it after
he started that then it would be then that that's why it
is totally מותר. mutar. Now again the question being as Michael said,
but if we're מתירים matirim certain things so if there is no
donkey or whatever why don't you allow it with the friend? At
least it's only a rabbinic problem and why don't you do שנים
שעשו? shnayim she'asu? So I really don't know the answer. I'll try
to see if there's some discussion about that. Let's read a little
bit more though about these solutions.
דאורייתא De'oraisa
is דאורייתא de'oraisa for them.
For the friend? It's not a full מלאכה. melachah. So you're it's
right he didn't do an עקירה. akira. You put it on your
friend as he was walking, he didn't do an עקירה. akira. All
right but that's what no, so you could there is a question
like when you have a technical loophole of a דאורייתא de'oraisa is
it just a דרבנן de'rabbanan or is it somehow like a דאורייתא
de'oraisa that you're exempt on? Okay so there is some of that
question, that might be relevant. אמר רב אדא בר אבא Amar Rav
Adda bar Abba היתה חבילתו מונחת על כתיפו haisa chavilasah munachas al
kteifo now get to Michael's question, I don't get it, let's just
do it for you for you, you've got your bundle on your
shoulder, so you know what רץ rutz רץ rutz עד שמגיע לביתו
ad she'magia l'veiso so just run home, you know you'll never stop
so you'll never you know and maybe you'll never have done even
an עקירה, akira, who knows? And you certainly wouldn't have done an
הנחה hanacha because you're not going to stop in רשות הרבים reshus
harabim so you're fine. So the גמרא Gemara says דווקא רץ davka
rutz that's only if you're running. אבל קלי קלי Aval kali kali
to walk slowly, קלי kali means like bit by bit, לא that
we won't let you do. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why? כיוון דליכא
היכירא Keivan d'leika hekeira
again since there's nothing you're doing to make it obvious and to
signal that there's an issue going on here, אתי למיעבד עקירה והנחה,
asi l'mevad akira v'hanacha, you'll come to do an עקירה akira and
an הנחה. hanacha. But here you know just as Michael said, you
know that's once you can do it, you know and violate certain
דרבנן de'rabbanan so you can even do it by... Who needs a
donkey, who needs a friend? You do it with a שינוי, shinuy,
put it above your head. All right, so then again, the question
is, right, did they allow everything or only the ones that they're
spelling out? Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. סוף סוף,
Sof sof, said the גמרא, Gemara one minute, כי מטי לביתיה אי
אפשר דלא קאי פורתא וקאיי מהאי לרשות היחיד? ki mati l'veiseh ee
efshar d'lo kai purta vekaye mehai l'rashus hayachid? I don't get it.
Once you get home, you're going to put it down. You're going
to stop, you're not going to keep on walking. So then at
least you're doing a הנחה. hanacha. So how do you deal with
that הנחה? hanacha? Now of course, as רש"י says, תוספות Tosafot says,
he says you could have done the ask that question from all
the cases. You've got it on your donkey, you've got it on
the, you know, whatever, so the donkey's going to have to stop
when you get home, so that's going to be, you know, the
הנחה. hanacha. But so let's see what the גמרא says. Now of
course, okay, so it says דזרק ליה כלאחר יד. dezarak leh k'le'achar
yad. So what happened is you put it down כלאחר יד. k'le'achar
yad. You don't put it down normally, you know, you let it
slip off of your back or something of that, so the עקירה
akira is with a שינוי. shinuy. Now what? The הנחה, hanacha, excuse
me, is with a שינוי. shinuy. Okay, now the interesting question is
is that was the גמרא assuming that there would have been a
דאורייתא de'oraisa here? Because if it got dark as you were walking,
then there was never an עקירה akira to begin with. And maybe
that's why the גמרא didn't ask this question before. In all the
other cases, you ensured that there wasn't an עקירה akira to begin
with, we weren't so concerned about the הנחה. hanacha. Here maybe we
assumed that there was an עקירה, akira, that you were standing and
then you started moving, and therefore we have to be really questioning
how do you avoid the הנחה? hanacha? Yes.
Isn't the עקירה akira just when the donkey or the person, I
guess, stops? I mean, wouldn't...
No, so that's the הנחה, hanacha, that's the end point. If I
put it on the donkey or the person as the donkey's walking,
then there's no עקירה, akira, the donkey stops, that's a הנחה, hanacha,
but it's only one end point. Then I take it off the
donkey, he starts walking again and I put it on him, so
again you don't have the start point, you're only going to have
the end point. So could be there the גמרא wasn't concerned about
how you put it down because you never had a start, you
never had an עקירה. akira. But if but in this case maybe
the גמרא is assuming that you can even start moving on שבת
Shabbat. and there would be an עקירה, akira, so it has to
say for how do you get it off you, how do you
do the הנחה? hanacha? Okay, so tomorrow we will pick up with
more general question about the prohibition of having your donkey do work
for you on שבת.